<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Rails | lolgramming]]></title>
  <link href="http://kamoh.github.io/blog/categories/rails/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kamoh.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-20T21:40:02-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kamoh.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ben Serviss]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[ben.serviss@flatironschool.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flatiron School: Week Seven]]></title>
    <link href="http://kamoh.github.io/blog/2014/07/19/flatiron-school-week-seven/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-19T18:57:47-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kamoh.github.io/blog/2014/07/19/flatiron-school-week-seven</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Something clicked this week. Between starting JavaScript on Wednesday, a great morning project using Spotify&rsquo;s API, and becoming even more comfortable withstanding torrents of new information, I&rsquo;m starting to feel like a programmer. It&rsquo;s not only that &ndash; when I look around at the other students, I no longer see people who came here because they wanted to learn how to program. I just see more programmers.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s an exhilarating, confounding, amazing feeling.</p>

<p>On Monday and Tuesday we barreled through most of the remaining Rails topics &ndash; some more details on using sessions to track user logins, Rails' asset pipeline, and AREL for handling complex database queries. AREL in particular was difficult to get through, since you are drilling down through AREL&rsquo;s syntax to the base SQL below, but it&rsquo;s easy to see how powerful it can be once you learn how to properly use it.</p>

<p>We also covered self-referential associations, in cases where you want to refer to a join table&rsquo;s column by a different name, and spent a little time looking at JSON&rsquo;s parsing with Spotify&rsquo;s web API (which was a lot of fun!).</p>

<p>On Wednesday, we dove into JavaScript. Most of us were excited to learn about it since we&rsquo;ve all been dying to start playing around with more user-facing elements of web development, and despite its cranky syntax, the consensus among most of the students is that JS and jQuery are great tools.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"> <div style="float:right"><script type="text/javascript" src="http://video.foxbusiness.com/v/embed.js?id=3670694770001&w=466&h=263">texty</script><p text-align="right"><i>Fox Business came to the campus a few weeks ago to do a segment.<br>I&rsquo;m literally coding with my back against the wall at 1:02 &amp; 3:40.</i></p></div></p>

<p>The most satisfying part of working with JavaScript has been how relatively easy it&rsquo;s been to pick up. Before Flatiron, when I&rsquo;d try to learn programming every other year or so, I would spend a week trying online courses and exercises before giving up in frustration.</p>

<p>Now, not only has it been weirdly smooth picking up an entirely new language, but I keep seeing so many similarities between JS and Ruby that make learning it even easier. Aside from components present in every programming language like strings and arrays, seeing similarities like how JavaScript&rsquo;s &lsquo;this&rsquo; mirror&rsquo;s Ruby&rsquo;s &lsquo;self&rsquo; makes it so much easier to get a grasp on a new language.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve also been going to the school on Saturday and Sunday for at least two weeks now, and plan on doing so until the end of the course. My group has started working on our group project, and we still have a lot of work to do before we present on August 5th. But even though I&rsquo;m literally there every day, I can&rsquo;t wait to finish this blog post and get back to work.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
