<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: WhenToWearIt | lolgramming]]></title>
  <link href="http://kamoh.github.io/blog/categories/whentowearit/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kamoh.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-06T00:24:21-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://kamoh.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ben Serviss]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[ben.serviss@flatironschool.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flatiron School Week Nine: Project Mode!]]></title>
    <link href="http://kamoh.github.io/blog/2014/08/02/flatiron-school-week-nine/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-02T22:12:45-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://kamoh.github.io/blog/2014/08/02/flatiron-school-week-nine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Things are starting to come to a head. We started off the week with our last crop of lectures on AJAX and using JSON in Rails, then began project mode!</p>

<p>From here on out until the end of the course, we&rsquo;ll be working in groups to make real web applications in lieu of lectures. The first week was a success &ndash; working on our own projects is immediately much more rewarding than completing assignments, and everyone managed to put together some really impressive sites by the end of the week.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"><img class="left" src="/images/8514/when_to_wear_it_main.png" width="550" title="WhenToWearIt" ></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m particularly proud of how my group&rsquo;s project turned out. It&rsquo;s called WhenToWearIt, and it&rsquo;s an outfit organizer that not only lets you organize your favorite outfit and clothing combinations, but it&rsquo;ll help you keep track of who you saw when you wore them to avoid seeming like you only own one outfit. Plus it also makes recommendations based on your wardrobe and preferences!</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"><img class="right" src="/images/8514/when_to_wear_it_dash.png" width="450" title="WhenToWearIt" ></p>

<p>While I&rsquo;m not exactly the target audience, I really liked the idea of producing something that women would find useful. I personally think they&rsquo;re an under-served audience in many ways, and more than a few female classmates said that they&rsquo;d use it when we release the finished version!</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s almost complete, but there&rsquo;s still some work to do to finish up the login system and some final polishing. I can&rsquo;t wait to finally launch something that will <em>actually</em> be useful to people!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
